<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Psychology / PCG, PCG (NP), PSY, PSY (NP) on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/social-psychology-/-pcg-pcg-np-psy-psy-np/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Psychology / PCG, PCG (NP), PSY, PSY (NP) on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 21:20:47 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/social-psychology-/-pcg-pcg-np-psy-psy-np/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 12: Attraction and Relationships</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-12/week-12-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 May 2025 21:20:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-12/week-12-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explores the dynamics of attraction and romantic relationships through empirical findings and theoretical frameworks in social psychology. It outlines factors predicting attraction, beginning with the propinquity effect, where frequent interaction increases the likelihood of forming relationships, influenced by both physical and functional distance. Mere exposure enhances liking, unless the person possesses negative qualities. Similarity—across attitudes, interests, appearance, and even genetics—is emphasized, with perceived similarity shown as a stronger predictor of attraction than actual similarity, particularly for long-term bonds. Reciprocal liking can override differences, and both sexes value physical attractiveness in practice, despite reported differences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 11: Prosocial Behavior</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-11/week-11-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 17:23:34 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-11/week-11-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A lecture on prosocial behaviour examined why individuals help others. The core of helping behaviour stems from several foundational motivations. Evolutionary psychology suggests that instincts drive helping, primarily through kin selection, favouring genetic relatives to ensure gene propagation. The norm of reciprocity, the expectation of future aid, and the contested idea of group selection, where altruistic groups might out-survive selfish ones, also contribute to this perspective. The Chernobyl disaster provided a stark example of extreme altruism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 10: Aggression</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-10/week-10-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 12:55:14 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-10/week-10-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture defined aggression as intentional behaviour aimed at causing physical harm or psychological pain, differentiating between hostile aggression (stemming from anger) and instrumental aggression (a means to an end).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An exploration into aggression&amp;rsquo;s origins questioned whether it is innate, learned, or optional. Evolutionary psychology posits that male physical aggression is genetically programmed for defence and gene perpetuation, while female aggression often serves to protect offspring. Animal studies, like Kuo’s kitten and rat experiment, show experience can modify instinct, though other research suggests some aggression is biologically hardwired. Testosterone is linked to aggression, particularly in males, but its relationship with behaviour is complex and reciprocal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 9: Prejudice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-9/week-9-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 12:51:08 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-9/week-9-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prejudice refers to a hostile or negative attitude toward people based solely on their group membership, encompassing cognitive, affective, and behavioral components. It operates bidirectionally, between majority and minority groups. The cognitive aspect involves categorization—a natural, adaptive process where the mind groups people based on traits—which may lead to stereotyping, defined as generalized beliefs about a group’s members. Stereotypes act as mental shortcuts but often distort reality, highlighting differences between groups while ignoring larger variations within them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 8: Conformity and Obedience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-8/week-8-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 15:29:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-8/week-8-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on conformity and obedience in social psychology outlined key forms of social influence: persuasion, compliance, conformity, and obedience. Persuasion involves deliberate attempts to change internal attitudes through communication, while compliance refers to behavioral changes in response to explicit or implicit requests without necessarily altering beliefs. Conformity entails adjusting behaviors or attitudes to align with group norms, often driven by the desire for social acceptance, and obedience involves following direct commands from authority figures, emphasizing external behavior changes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIDTERM: Social Psychology / PCG, PCG (NP), PSY, PSY (NP)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/midterm/sp-psy-midterm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:48:40 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/midterm/sp-psy-midterm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;midterm-content&#34;&gt;Midterm Content:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 3: The Self &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 4: Social Cognition &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 5: Attitudes &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 6: Persuasion &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 7: Groups&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Groups</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-7/week-7-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 09:44:14 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-7/week-7-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A group is defined as two or more individuals who interact and influence each other, often forming around shared goals, needs, or identities. Evolutionarily, groups enhanced survival by facilitating cooperation in tasks like hunting and caregiving. They also provide social norms and roles that guide behavior, though these can sometimes suppress individuality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Groups typically consist of three to six members and are shaped by norms, roles, cohesiveness, and diversity. While cohesiveness strengthens bonds, it can hinder performance if harmony is prioritized over effective decision-making. Diversity, especially in race and experience, can enhance group outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Persuasion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-6/week-6-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 15:00:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-6/week-6-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on persuasion explored various facets of persuasive communication and its impact on attitude change. Persuasion involves messages aimed at altering attitudes and behaviors, with key elements including the communicator, the message, the medium, and audience characteristics. The lecture highlighted the third-person effect, where individuals believe they are less influenced by advertisements than others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attitude change often results from social influence and persuasive communication, with emotional and cognitive appeals playing significant roles. Fear appeals are effective when paired with solutions, while advertising leverages affective and cognitive appeals based on cultural contexts. The lecture also discussed self-generated persuasion, where individuals change attitudes by generating their own arguments, and cognitive dissonance, which occurs when actions contradict beliefs, prompting attitude alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Attitudes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-5/week-5-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 13:33:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-5/week-5-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attitudes are evaluations of people, objects, and ideas, shaped by genetics and social experiences. They have three components: cognitive (based on beliefs), affective (rooted in emotions and values), and behavioral (inferred from actions). Attitudes can be explicit (consciously endorsed) or implicit (unconscious and shaped by early experiences).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Their influence on behavior depends on accessibility and context. Spontaneous actions align with strong, readily available attitudes, while deliberate behavior follows the Theory of Planned Behavior, which considers specific attitudes, social norms, and perceived control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Social Cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-4/week-4-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 11:43:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-4/week-4-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social cognition explored how individuals perceive and interpret the social world. It highlighted the distinction between automatic and controlled thinking. Automatic thinking is non-conscious, effortless, and involves the use of schemas—mental structures that help organize social information. These schemas are influenced by culture and can be primed by recent experiences, affecting judgments and decisions. The lecture also discussed the self-fulfilling prophecy, where expectations about others can influence their behavior, making those expectations come true.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: The Self</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-3/week-3-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:34:06 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-3/week-3-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explored the concept of self, focusing on self-concept, self-awareness, and self-perception. Self-concept is defined as the beliefs individuals hold about their personal attributes, with self-schema acting as a cognitive framework guiding perception and evaluation. The development of self-concept begins in early childhood, with human self-recognition emerging between 18-24 months. Cultural influences shape self-concept, with independent and interdependent views of self highlighting differences in self-definition based on personal attributes versus relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-2/week-2-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:08 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-2/week-2-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social psychology explored various questions about human behavior and social interactions, such as how people perceive and reason about the social world, the dynamics of group membership, factors influencing aggression and prejudice, and the reasons behind interpersonal attraction and cooperation. It also examined the effectiveness of political advertisements and the motivations for helping behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address these questions, the lecture emphasized the importance of the scientific method, which involves generating hypotheses, testing them, and communicating findings. It distinguished between science, pseudoscience, protoscience, and nonscience, highlighting the need for falsifiability in scientific hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-1/week-1-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:35 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-1/week-1-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture treated the profound effects of social influence and isolation on human behavior and cognition. It highlighted a study involving nine polar expeditioners in Antarctica, revealing significant reductions in the volume of the dentate gyrus due to social isolation, underscoring the brain&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability to such conditions. The lecture also examined the tragic events of the Jonestown massacre, illustrating the extreme power of social influence under cult leader Jim Jones, where 914 individuals perished after being coerced into a mass suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
