<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ethical, Legal, and Professional Issues in Humanities and Social Sciences on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ethical, Legal, and Professional Issues in Humanities and Social Sciences on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:15:18 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURES 5 and 6 (Self-study)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-5-6/week-5-6-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:15:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-5-6/week-5-6-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lectures-for-self-study&#34;&gt;Lectures for self-study:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidentiality: Ethical and Legal Issues (WEEK 5)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter covers the essential aspects of maintaining confidentiality within professional environments, highlighting both ethical considerations and legal obligations. Understanding these principles is crucial for your future roles.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Boundaries and Multiple Relationships (WEEK 6)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This section addresses the complexities of maintaining professional boundaries and handling multiple relationships. It provides guidance on avoiding conflicts of interest and ensuring ethical interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Client Rights and Counselor Responsibilities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-4/week-4-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 12:05:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-4/week-4-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on the ethical, legal, and professional responsibilities of counselors, emphasizing the importance of client rights. Central to ethical practice is the concept of informed consent, which allows clients to make autonomous decisions about their therapy. This process involves providing clients with comprehensive information about therapy goals, risks, benefits, and procedures, thereby enhancing the therapeutic alliance and minimizing misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Informed consent is not a one-time event but an ongoing process that requires regular updates and check-ins to empower clients and maintain a collaborative partnership. Legal aspects of informed consent demand that clients understand the information, give consent voluntarily, and are competent to do so. Documentation of informed consent is crucial for legal protection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Values and the Helping Relationship</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-3/week-3-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:54:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-3/week-3-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In counseling, values significantly shape the therapeutic process. Counselors must be conscious of their own values and avoid imposing personal beliefs on clients, adhering to ethical guidelines that emphasize cultural awareness in value formation. The debate between objectivity and value neutrality highlights that values inevitably influence counseling relationships, affecting various aspects. Ethical responsibility requires counselors to monitor how they communicate values, considering power dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Value imposition occurs when counselors attempt to influence clients to adopt their values, either actively or passively. Ethical codes, such as those from the ACA and ASCA, caution against this practice. When facing value conflicts, counselors should not refer clients merely due to disagreements but only when lacking necessary skills. Referrals should be based on self-awareness of competence limitations, prioritizing client needs over personal beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: The Counselor as a Person and as a Professional</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-2/week-2-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:16:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-2/week-2-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-awareness is crucial for therapists to maintain ethical practice, as a lack of it can hinder client progress and shift focus from client needs to therapist inadequacies. Therapists must recognize their personal needs, unresolved issues, and vulnerabilities. Many counselors are motivated by their own life struggles, but their needs should not overshadow client growth. It&amp;rsquo;s unrealistic to expect therapists to have resolved all personal issues; the key is how they manage them. Personal therapy offers therapists insight into client experiences, promotes self-care, and enhances empathy and competence. Graduate clinicians who undergo personal therapy develop stronger therapeutic alliances and gain valuable insights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Professional Ethics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-1/week-1-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:52 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-1/week-1-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explores ethics, a philosophical branch examining moral judgments and their nature, divided into subfields like normative, applied, metaethics, and descriptive ethics. Professional ethics dictate acceptable conduct within professions, often guided by a code of ethics. These codes provide guidelines for ethical conduct, decision-making, and professional behavior, ensuring accountability and client welfare. Ethical dilemmas, such as confidentiality versus the duty to warn, illustrate the challenges faced by professionals. Common themes in ethics codes include client welfare, competence, cultural respect, and confidentiality. However, these codes have limitations, being broad and sometimes conflicting with laws or cultural norms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
