<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Statistics on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Statistics on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 16:19:40 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Submit Homework via Microsoft Forms Only</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/notices/homework-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 16:19:40 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/notices/homework-submission/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed that some of you are still sending your homework assignments through email for the Statistics course, despite my multiple reminders and instructions. Please remember that &lt;strong&gt;&lt;u class=&#34;text-underline&#34;&gt;all homework must be submitted via Microsoft Forms&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. The links to the assignment forms are available on my blog for each of the lectures.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I won’t be accepting any assignments sent by email, so make sure to use the correct submission method. for this, you need a working university issued &lt;strong&gt;&lt;u class=&#34;text-underline&#34;&gt;@ibu.edu.mk email address&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This ensures that your work is properly tracked and graded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Basics of Inferential Statistics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-3/stat-post-lecture-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 20:32:42 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-3/stat-post-lecture-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Inferential statistics allow researchers to make general conclusions based on sample data, extending their findings beyond the participants in a study. Key concepts include scores, outliers, and measures of central tendency (mean, median, mode). Variability is measured using variance and standard deviation, which reflect how spread out the scores are from the mean. A normal distribution follows a bell-shaped curve, which is symmetric and unimodal. The central limit theorem explains that, with enough random influences, a precise normal curve results. Z-scores express how far a particular score is from the mean in terms of standard deviations, offering insight into its position within the distribution. The normal curve allows us to predict the percentage of scores falling above or below any point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Central Tendency and Variability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-2/stat-post-lecture-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 20:13:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-2/stat-post-lecture-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture covered the concepts of central tendency and variability, essential tools in descriptive statistics. Central tendency refers to finding a single value that represents a set of scores. The three primary measures are the mean, mode, and median. The mean is the arithmetic average, calculated by summing all values and dividing by the number of values. It is sensitive to outliers, while the median is a more robust measure, representing the middle score when data is ordered. The mode is the most frequent score in a distribution and is typically used for nominal data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Measurement, Data, Distributions, Tables, and Graphs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-1/stat-post-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 14:18:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-1/stat-post-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture covered foundational concepts in statistics, focusing on measurement, data, distributions, tables, and graphs. It began by emphasizing the importance of statistics for conducting research, understanding scientific literature, and developing critical thinking. The field of statistics was divided into two main areas: descriptive statistics, which involves summarizing and organizing data, and inferential statistics, which focuses on drawing conclusions from sample data to generalize about populations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Key definitions were introduced, such as data, variables, and different levels of measurement. Variables were classified as either discrete or continuous, and the types of data—qualitative and quantitative—were explained. The levels of measurement were outlined, including nominal, ordinal, interval, and ratio, each providing different levels of information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Statistics&#39; Course Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:44:55 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to the fundamental concepts of statistics in psychology, emphasizing data analysis and interpretation. Topics covered include data measurement, central tendency, variability, inferential statistics, hypothesis testing, t-tests, ANOVA, correlation, regression, and chi-square tests. Students will learn how to apply statistical techniques to psychological research, interpret results, and understand the importance of statistical significance, effect size, and power. This course provides essential skills for analyzing psychological data and conducting research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
