<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 13:48:30 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Cognitive Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-1/cp-post-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 13:48:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-1/cp-post-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;homework-assignment&#34;&gt;Homework assignment:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;reading-materials&#34;&gt;Reading materials:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Main textbook:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u class=&#34;text-underline&#34;&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Goldstein, E. B. (2019). &lt;em&gt;Cognitive psychology: Connecting mind, research, and everyday experience&lt;/em&gt; (5th ed.). Cengage Learning. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/2h12zgk69fuliyu/cognitive-psychology-connecting-mind-research-and-everyday-experience.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Supplementary textbook:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;u class=&#34;text-underline&#34;&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Sternberg, R. J., &amp;amp; Sternberg, K. (2017). &lt;em&gt;Cognitive psychology&lt;/em&gt; (7th ed.). Cengage Learning. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/gmkqe115xmhpe2fcy9xi7/cognitive-psychology.pdf?rlkey=6fx71txlfh50yzvpmdtyuzn3c&amp;amp;dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;(PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Psychology as Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-1/itp-post-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 12:47:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-1/itp-post-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Psychology is the scientific study of mental processes and behavior. It systematically examines how the brain operates, its structure, and how it influences observable actions. To understand behavior, psychologists analyze three levels: the brain, the individual, and group dynamics. Psychological inquiry often contrasts scientific methods with intuition. Science relies on empirical data and systematic experimentation, while intuition involves more automatic and emotional thinking. Psychologists prefer empirical methods to ensure objectivity and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Human and Artificial Intelligence&#39; Course Reading Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/human-and-artificial-intelligence/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 21:13:36 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/human-and-artificial-intelligence/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course explores the nature of intelligence, both human and artificial. Topics include theoretical frameworks, types of human intelligence, and the impact of biological and environmental factors on its development. The course also introduces artificial intelligence, examining functional aspects, machine learning, and large language models. By comparing human and artificial intelligence, students will explore concepts like machine consciousness and the ethical and societal implications of AI, fostering critical insights into this evolving field.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Statistics&#39; Course Reading Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:44:55 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to the fundamental concepts of statistics in psychology, emphasizing data analysis and interpretation. Topics covered include data measurement, central tendency, variability, inferential statistics, hypothesis testing, t-tests, ANOVA, correlation, regression, and chi-square tests. Students will learn how to apply statistical techniques to psychological research, interpret results, and understand the importance of statistical significance, effect size, and power. This course provides essential skills for analyzing psychological data and conducting research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Cognitive Process&#39; Course Reading Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:38:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course provides an overview of the fundamental processes involved in human cognition. Topics include perception, attention, memory, language, problem-solving, decision-making, and creativity. The course also explores cognitive neuroscience, conceptual knowledge, visual imagery, and human intelligence. Special focus is given to cognitive disorders, offering insights into how these processes can malfunction. Students will gain a deeper understanding of how the brain supports mental functions and how cognitive processes impact everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Introduction to Psychology&#39; Course Reading Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 16:49:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course provides a broad overview of key concepts in psychology, exploring the scientific study of behavior and mental processes. Topics include brain function, sensation and perception, learning, memory, emotion, intelligence, personality, and social interactions. The course also examines psychological disorders, lifespan development, and the application of psychology in workplaces through industrial-organizational psychology. Students will gain a foundational understanding of psychological science and its practical applications in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grading System Information</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/grading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 12:38:33 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/grading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Students at IBU can enter their exams the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Midterm/final model of exams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Grade structure&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Midterm exam 40 CP&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Final Exam 40 CP&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Activity 20 CP&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Midterm Exam&lt;/em&gt;: Student will be allowed to enter the midterm exam, if s/he has completed their debt obligations&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final Exam&lt;/em&gt;: The student will be allowed to enter the final exam if they meet the minimum attendance&#xA;criteria, have no debt obligations and if they have gained a minimum of 10 CP in the midterm&#xA;exam&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to your professor&#39;s blog!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 12:38:14 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello Students,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my IBU Blog. We are about to begin a new 2024/2025 academic year at the International Balkan University. I created this blog to facilitate our communication and to reduce the number of emails. This should help us prevent misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When many individuals attempt to communicate via email, it can become confusing and slow. This happens because a single email account can become overloaded, making it difficult to keep track of all the messages. Teachers are also occupied with other responsibilities and may not always be able to respond promptly. That&amp;rsquo;s why I chose to consolidate all my updates in one place online—this blog—for everyone to access.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
