<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:54:18 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Values and the Helping Relationship</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-3/week-3-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:54:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-3/week-3-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In counseling, values significantly shape the therapeutic process. Counselors must be conscious of their own values and avoid imposing personal beliefs on clients, adhering to ethical guidelines that emphasize cultural awareness in value formation. The debate between objectivity and value neutrality highlights that values inevitably influence counseling relationships, affecting various aspects. Ethical responsibility requires counselors to monitor how they communicate values, considering power dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Value imposition occurs when counselors attempt to influence clients to adopt their values, either actively or passively. Ethical codes, such as those from the ACA and ASCA, caution against this practice. When facing value conflicts, counselors should not refer clients merely due to disagreements but only when lacking necessary skills. Referrals should be based on self-awareness of competence limitations, prioritizing client needs over personal beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: The Self</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-3/week-3-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:52:39 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-3/week-3-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explored the concept of self, focusing on self-concept, self-awareness, and self-perception. Self-concept is defined as the beliefs individuals hold about their personal attributes, with self-schema acting as a cognitive framework guiding perception and evaluation. The development of self-concept begins in early childhood, with human self-recognition emerging between 18-24 months. Cultural influences shape self-concept, with independent and interdependent views of self highlighting differences in self-definition based on personal attributes versus relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: The Self</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-3/week-3-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:34:06 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-3/week-3-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explored the concept of self, focusing on self-concept, self-awareness, and self-perception. Self-concept is defined as the beliefs individuals hold about their personal attributes, with self-schema acting as a cognitive framework guiding perception and evaluation. The development of self-concept begins in early childhood, with human self-recognition emerging between 18-24 months. Cultural influences shape self-concept, with independent and interdependent views of self highlighting differences in self-definition based on personal attributes versus relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Communication Styles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-3/week-3-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:28:49 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-3/week-3-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on the role of Graphical User Interfaces (GUIs) in modern computing, emphasizing their visual interaction through windows, icons, and menus. It highlighted the importance of informing learners about the nature of their educational experience and outlined key components for building effective computer learning materials, such as introductions, study time advice, and context-sensitive help.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture compared computer-based learning (CBL) with traditional educational approaches, noting that CBL offers individualized instruction and flexible learning environments, unlike the one-to-many communication in traditional settings. CBL allows for one-to-one communication and varied media use, providing a more interactive and personalized learning experience. It also reduces costs as the number of students increases, unlike traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: The Counselor as a Person and as a Professional</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-2/week-2-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:16:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-2/week-2-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-awareness is crucial for therapists to maintain ethical practice, as a lack of it can hinder client progress and shift focus from client needs to therapist inadequacies. Therapists must recognize their personal needs, unresolved issues, and vulnerabilities. Many counselors are motivated by their own life struggles, but their needs should not overshadow client growth. It&amp;rsquo;s unrealistic to expect therapists to have resolved all personal issues; the key is how they manage them. Personal therapy offers therapists insight into client experiences, promotes self-care, and enhances empathy and competence. Graduate clinicians who undergo personal therapy develop stronger therapeutic alliances and gain valuable insights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-2/week-2-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-2/week-2-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social psychology explored various questions about human behavior and social interactions, such as how people perceive and reason about the social world, the dynamics of group membership, factors influencing aggression and prejudice, and the reasons behind interpersonal attraction and cooperation. It also examined the effectiveness of political advertisements and the motivations for helping behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address these questions, the lecture emphasized the importance of the scientific method, which involves generating hypotheses, testing them, and communicating findings. It distinguished between science, pseudoscience, protoscience, and nonscience, highlighting the need for falsifiability in scientific hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-2/week-2-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:08 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-2/week-2-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social psychology explored various questions about human behavior and social interactions, such as how people perceive and reason about the social world, the dynamics of group membership, factors influencing aggression and prejudice, and the reasons behind interpersonal attraction and cooperation. It also examined the effectiveness of political advertisements and the motivations for helping behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address these questions, the lecture emphasized the importance of the scientific method, which involves generating hypotheses, testing them, and communicating findings. It distinguished between science, pseudoscience, protoscience, and nonscience, highlighting the need for falsifiability in scientific hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Computers, Interactions, and Learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-2/week-2-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-2/week-2-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A computer is a programmable device capable of storing, retrieving, and processing data based on instructions. Its key components include storage devices like RAM and hard disks, and the CPU, which controls other parts of the computer. Learning is defined as acquiring knowledge or skills through experience, study, or teaching, resulting in relatively permanent changes. Various learning approaches include the behavioral, cognitive, and constructivist methods, each emphasizing different aspects of the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Professional Ethics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-1/week-1-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:52 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-1/week-1-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explores ethics, a philosophical branch examining moral judgments and their nature, divided into subfields like normative, applied, metaethics, and descriptive ethics. Professional ethics dictate acceptable conduct within professions, often guided by a code of ethics. These codes provide guidelines for ethical conduct, decision-making, and professional behavior, ensuring accountability and client welfare. Ethical dilemmas, such as confidentiality versus the duty to warn, illustrate the challenges faced by professionals. Common themes in ethics codes include client welfare, competence, cultural respect, and confidentiality. However, these codes have limitations, being broad and sometimes conflicting with laws or cultural norms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-1/week-1-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-1/week-1-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture treated the profound effects of social influence and isolation on human behavior and cognition. It highlighted a study involving nine polar expeditioners in Antarctica, revealing significant reductions in the volume of the dentate gyrus due to social isolation, underscoring the brain&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability to such conditions. The lecture also examined the tragic events of the Jonestown massacre, illustrating the extreme power of social influence under cult leader Jim Jones, where 914 individuals perished after being coerced into a mass suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-1/week-1-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:35 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-1/week-1-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture treated the profound effects of social influence and isolation on human behavior and cognition. It highlighted a study involving nine polar expeditioners in Antarctica, revealing significant reductions in the volume of the dentate gyrus due to social isolation, underscoring the brain&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability to such conditions. The lecture also examined the tragic events of the Jonestown massacre, illustrating the extreme power of social influence under cult leader Jim Jones, where 914 individuals perished after being coerced into a mass suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Computer Aided Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-1/week-1-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:25 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-1/week-1-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Computer Aided Education introductory lecture explored the integration of computers into the educational process. The lecture began by defining key terms: computer, aided, and education. It then posed critical questions about the role of computers in enhancing learning, their potential to increase student interest, and whether they could replace teachers. The discussion also considered the future importance of digital literacy compared to traditional literacy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture covered various aspects of computer-aided education, including interaction and learning, communication styles, and types of computer-based learning materials. It looked into assessment methods and the use of text, color, graphics, multimedia, online learning, and networking. Content and layout design were emphasized, along with using computers for research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to your professor&#39;s blog!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 13:56:27 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m so excited to welcome you to my blog. Whether you’re looking for study materials, homework updates, or just a place to share ideas, this is where it’s all going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about this blog is that it’s going to help us stay organized and connected without drowning in a sea of emails. Instead of sending out a bunch of messages that might get lost in the inbox, I’ll be posting lecture summaries, homework assignments, important announcements, reminders, and updates right here. That way, you’ll always know where to look for the latest info, and we can avoid any confusion or missed messages. The blog is designed to make your life easier, so you can focus on learning and collaborating without the stress of keeping track of a million different things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
