<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 21:31:20 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 9: Problem Solving and Creativity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-9/cp-2025-12-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 21:31:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-9/cp-2025-12-03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychologists define a problem as a situation where an obstacle exists between a present state and a goal state, necessitating specific actions to bridge the gap. The Gestalt approach emphasizes that success depends heavily on how a problem is represented in the mind, often requiring a process of restructuring or reorganizing that representation. This restructuring facilitates insight, a sudden realization or &amp;ldquo;Aha!&amp;rdquo; experience that differs fundamentally from the gradual, step-by-step progress seen in analytical or non-insight problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 8: T Test for Independent Means</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-8/stat-2025-12-02/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 20:38:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-8/stat-2025-12-02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The t-test for independent means functions as the primary hypothesis-testing procedure for comparing two entirely separate groups of participants, such as an experimental group receiving a specific intervention and a control group receiving a standard protocol. Unlike dependent means tests which analyze repeated measures or matched scores within a single group, this analysis requires that all scores be independent of one another, meaning no participant belongs to both groups. The test is specifically applicable when the true population variance is unknown and must be estimated using data derived from the samples themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IN-CLASS PRESENTATIONS: Cognitive Process</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/activity/in-class-presentations-cognitive-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 22:39:13 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/activity/in-class-presentations-cognitive-process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructions&#34;&gt;Instructions:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;step-1-choose-an-article&#34;&gt;Step 1: Choose an Article&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Go to Google Scholar. Find a full-text peer-reviewed, empirical research article (one that collects actual data, not a literature review or meta-analysis) on a topic that interests you. Tip: Don’t pick a 50-page paper with six different experiments. Pick a standard paper with a clear, singular focus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;step-2-the--structure&#34;&gt;Step 2: The  Structure&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You only have 3 minutes. That means you cannot read the abstract to us. You must extract the core narrative. Structure your talk using these five specific pillars:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IN-CLASS PRESENTATIONS: Statistics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/activity/in-class-presentations-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 22:15:21 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/activity/in-class-presentations-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructions&#34;&gt;Instructions:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;step-1-choose-an-article&#34;&gt;Step 1: Choose an Article&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Go to Google Scholar. Find a full-text peer-reviewed, empirical research article (one that collects actual data, not a literature review or meta-analysis) on a topic that interests you. Tip: Don’t pick a 50-page paper with six different experiments. Pick a standard paper with a clear, singular focus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;step-2-the--structure&#34;&gt;Step 2: The  Structure&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You only have 3 minutes. That means you cannot read the abstract to us. You must extract the core narrative. Structure your talk using these five specific pillars:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 8: Language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-8/cp-2025-11-26/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 21:31:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-8/cp-2025-11-26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Human language is defined as a system of communication utilizing sounds or symbols to express feelings, thoughts, ideas, and experiences. Its defining characteristic is creativity, which stems from a structure that is both hierarchical and rule-based, allowing for the generation of unique sequences. Psycholinguistics examines the psychological processes behind this ability, breaking language down into phonology (sounds), syntax (structure), semantics (meaning), and pragmatics (implied meaning).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the lexical level, word frequency heavily influences processing speed, with high-frequency words eliciting faster responses than low-frequency ones. Readers must also navigate lexical ambiguity, where context and meaning dominance help select the correct interpretation of multi-meaning words. When combining words into sentences, the mind engages in parsing. The Garden Path Model suggests this is done via heuristics like late closure, while the constraint-based approach argues that syntax, semantics, and context serve as simultaneous constraints to guide understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Introduction to t Tests: Single Sample and Dependent Means</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-7/stat-2025-11-25/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 20:38:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-7/stat-2025-11-25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Real-world psychological research rarely offers access to the true population variance, making the standard Z test impractical for most experimental studies. To overcome this limitation, the t test (or &amp;ldquo;Student&amp;rsquo;s t&amp;rdquo;) serves as the standard hypothesis-testing procedure when the population variance is unknown and must be estimated directly from sample data. Because the variance of a sample naturally tends to be smaller than the variance of the population from which it is drawn, it is considered a biased estimate. To correct for this bias, the calculation for the estimated population variance ($S^2$) utilizes degrees of freedom ($df=N−1$) in the denominator rather than the total sample size ($N$), ensuring an unbiased estimate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Visual Imagery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-7/cp-2025-11-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-7/cp-2025-11-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Visual imagery is defined as the ability to recreate the sensory world in the absence of physical stimuli, a capacity that extends beyond vision to include taste, smell, and touch. Historically, the study of imagery fluctuated, moving from Wundt’s view that images are essential to thought, through the &amp;ldquo;imageless thought&amp;rdquo; debate and Behaviorist rejection, before being revived during the Cognitive Revolution. Alan Paivio’s work on the conceptual peg hypothesis later demonstrated that concrete nouns create mental anchors, making them easier to remember than abstract concepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Statistical Significance, Decision Errors, Effect Size, and Power</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-6/stat-2025-11-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-6/stat-2025-11-18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture builds upon the fundamentals of hypothesis testing to explore the critical concepts of decision errors, effect size, and statistical power. While standard hypothesis testing determines whether a sample outcome is unlikely under the null hypothesis, this binary decision-making process is prone to error. A Type I error (α) involves rejecting the null hypothesis when it is actually true—essentially a false positive. A Type II error (β) occurs when one fails to reject a false null hypothesis, resulting in a false negative.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Concepts of Probability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-4/aqrm-2025-11-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 16:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-4/aqrm-2025-11-17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Probability theory serves as the mathematical foundation for all statistics, playing a critical role in psychology for designing studies, analyzing data, and interpreting results. It allows researchers to distinguish real effects from chance, model cognitive processes involving uncertainty, and correct common human misjudgments regarding random events. Furthermore, probability is essential for evidence-based practice, such as estimating the likelihood of patient improvement under specific therapies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A basic understanding begins with the &amp;ldquo;simple experiment,&amp;rdquo; a repeatable process yielding a single, unambiguous outcome from a &amp;ldquo;sample space&amp;rdquo; of all possible results. Probability definitions vary: the Analytic view relies on logical, equally likely outcomes; the Frequentist view depends on long-run relative frequency from repeated trials; and the Subjective view represents a degree of belief, which is central to Bayesian reasoning. Calculations often utilize Venn diagrams to visualize relationships such as the &amp;ldquo;intersection&amp;rdquo; (outcomes common to multiple events) and the &amp;ldquo;union&amp;rdquo; (outcomes in either event).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computer Aided Education Midterm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/midterm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 22:28:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/midterm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the students who have Computer Aided Education course registered, the Midterm deadline is &lt;strong&gt;14 Nov 2025&lt;/strong&gt; for project submission via email.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Send your PowerPoint project that has to include at least the following:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Has to be on an educational academic topic.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Has to work in the PowerPoint Kiosk presentation mode (it means you have to build all functionality and navigation yourself).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Has to be readable and follow the principle of content chunking.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Has to have organized text and font use (for headings, subheadings, body content, feedback, annotations, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Must have at least 20 slides.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;reading-materials&#34;&gt;Reading materials:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Designing Computer-Based Learning Material.  (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ibuit-my.sharepoint.com/:b:/g/personal/kirjakovski_ibu_edu_mk/Ebw6bkjN3TJOg5fCR3Mr7PQBteAScK2-OuTMT83_qQT7mA?e=Evtl5o&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DOWNLOAD PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Conceptual Knowledge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-6/cp-2025-11-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 16:42:04 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-6/cp-2025-11-05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture examines conceptual knowledge, the system that enables people to recognize objects and make inferences about their properties. This knowledge is organized into concepts (mental representations, like &amp;ldquo;cat&amp;rdquo;) and categories (groups of objects, like &amp;ldquo;furniture&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Early attempts to categorize using rigid definitions (the definitional approach) were found to be inadequate, as many category members (like different types of chairs) do not meet all criteria. This led to the &lt;strong&gt;Prototype Approach&lt;/strong&gt;, which posits that categories are formed around a single &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; member, or prototype. New items are judged based on their &amp;ldquo;typicality,&amp;rdquo; or resemblance to this prototype. This explains the &amp;ldquo;typicality effect,&amp;rdquo; where highly typical objects (like &amp;ldquo;sparrow&amp;rdquo; for &amp;ldquo;bird&amp;rdquo;) are verified more rapidly than atypical ones (like &amp;ldquo;penguin&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Hypothesis Test with Means of Samples</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-5/stat-2025-11-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 21:29:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-5/stat-2025-11-04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture provides a review of Z-scores and the foundational five-step hypothesis-testing process. It then transitions from testing a single individual to testing a sample with multiple individuals ($N&amp;gt;1$). This shift requires a new comparison distribution: the &lt;strong&gt;distribution of means&lt;/strong&gt;, also known as the sampling distribution of the mean.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture details the three key characteristics of this distribution, which are defined by the &lt;strong&gt;Central Limit Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean:&lt;/strong&gt; The mean of the distribution of means ($\mu_M$) is identical to the mean of the population of individuals ($\mu$).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variance:&lt;/strong&gt; The distribution is less spread out. Its variance ($\sigma_M^2$) is the population variance ($\sigma^2$) divided by the sample size ($N$). Its standard deviation, $\sigma_M = \sigma / \sqrt{N}$, is called the &lt;strong&gt;standard error of the mean (SEM)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shape:&lt;/strong&gt; The distribution of means will be approximately normal if the population is normal, or if the sample size is 30 or more, regardless of the original population&amp;rsquo;s shape.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This framework allows for the &lt;strong&gt;Z-test&lt;/strong&gt;, a procedure used when the population variance is known. The formula adapts the Z-score to compare a sample mean ($M$) to the population mean: $Z = (M - \mu_M) / \sigma_M$.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Descriptive Statistics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-3/aqrm-2025-11-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2025 16:49:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-3/aqrm-2025-11-03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture begins by establishing the fundamental concepts of &lt;strong&gt;populations&lt;/strong&gt; versus &lt;strong&gt;samples&lt;/strong&gt;, distinguishing between the entire group of interest and the subset being studied. It clarifies the difference between population parameters and their corresponding sample statistics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Following this, the focus shifts to &lt;strong&gt;descriptive statistics&lt;/strong&gt;, starting with measures of &lt;strong&gt;central tendency&lt;/strong&gt;—single values that represent the center of a dataset. The three primary measures are explored: the &lt;strong&gt;mean&lt;/strong&gt;, or arithmetic average, which is widely used but sensitive to outliers; the &lt;strong&gt;mode&lt;/strong&gt;, the most frequently occurring value, ideal for nominal (categorical) data; and the &lt;strong&gt;median&lt;/strong&gt;, the middle score in an ordered distribution, which is preferred for skewed data. The presentation also briefly introduces other measures like the weighted, trimmed, and geometric means, each suited for specific analytical situations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Memory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-5/cp-2025-10-29/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 16:42:04 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-5/cp-2025-10-29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Memory is the process of retaining, retrieving, and using information after the original stimulus is gone. The classic Modal Model of Memory breaks this process into three structural stages. First, Sensory Memory briefly holds all incoming sensory information for less than a second. Sperling&amp;rsquo;s partial report experiments demonstrated that while sensory memory has a large capacity, the information fades rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Information attended to moves into Short-Term Memory (STM), a store with a limited duration and capacity. Without rehearsal, information in STM lasts only about 15-20 seconds. While traditionally thought to hold &amp;ldquo;seven plus or minus two&amp;rdquo; items, modern change detection studies suggest the capacity is closer to four items. This capacity is also affected by information complexity, not just item count. However, capacity can be expanded by chunking—grouping small units into larger, meaningful ones. The concept of STM was refined into Working Memory (WM), which is not just a passive store, but an active system for manipulating information for complex tasks. This multi-component model includes the Phonological Loop for verbal and auditory information and the Visuospatial Sketch Pad for visual and spatial information. These &amp;ldquo;slave systems&amp;rdquo; are coordinated by the Central Executive, which directs attention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Introduction to Hypothesis Testing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-4/stat-2025-10-28/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 16:16:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-4/stat-2025-10-28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture introduces hypothesis testing, the formal procedure used to decide if the results from a sample study support a theory or prediction about a population. This process involves using known sample statistics (like the sample mean, $M$) to make inferences about unknown population parameters (like the population mean, $\mu$). This logic is grounded in the properties of the normal curve, a symmetrical, bell-shaped distribution where a Z score indicates a specific score&amp;rsquo;s location and probability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Working with Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-2/aqrm-2025-10-27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 16:49:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-2/aqrm-2025-10-27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture covers the fundamental aspects of working with quantitative data in research. It begins by exploring Data Theory, defining data not just as raw facts or numbers but as information collected for examination. Data isn&amp;rsquo;t merely &amp;ldquo;given&amp;rdquo; (datum) but actively &amp;ldquo;taken&amp;rdquo; (capta), shaped by the ideas, technologies, and contexts involved in its production. This Non-Neutrality Principle highlights that data are socio-technical constructs, never truly raw or objective.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data can be classified in various ways: discrete (countable) vs. continuous (measurable); small vs. big data (characterized by Volume, Velocity, Variety); structured, semi-structured, or unstructured. Data originates from different sources (captured, exhaust, derived) and can be primary (collected by the researcher) or secondary (collected by others). The DIKW framework illustrates the progression from raw Data to Information (organized), Knowledge (understood patterns), and Wisdom (applied understanding).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Attention</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-4/cp-2025-10-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 16:02:26 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-4/cp-2025-10-22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture defines attention as the mind taking possession of one object or train of thought, implying a withdrawal from some things to deal effectively with others. This process manifests as selective attention (focusing), divided attention (multitasking), and attentional capture. Early models sought to explain when selection occurs. Broadbent&amp;rsquo;s filter model proposed an early filter based on physical characteristics, blocking unattended information. However, this was challenged by the &amp;ldquo;cocktail party effect&amp;rdquo; (hearing one&amp;rsquo;s name) and findings that meaning could be processed from an unattended ear. Treisman’s attenuation model modified this, suggesting the unattended message is weakened, not blocked, allowing salient information (like one&amp;rsquo;s name) to pass. In contrast, late selection models proposed that all stimuli are processed for meaning before selection. The Load Theory of Attention addresses how we ignore distractions, positing that this depends on the task&amp;rsquo;s perceptual load. Low-load (easy) tasks leave spare processing capacity that &amp;ldquo;spills over&amp;rdquo; to process distractors, making distraction more likely. High-load (hard) tasks consume all resources, leaving none to process distractors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Basics of Inferential Statistics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-3/stat-2025-10-21/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 15:55:50 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-3/stat-2025-10-21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture introduces inferential statistics, the procedures used for drawing conclusions that extend beyond the specific scores collected in a study. It establishes the fundamental distinction between a population (the entire group of interest) and a sample (the particular group of people studied). Research involves studying a sample and using its sample statistics (like the mean, M, and standard deviation, SD) to make inferences about the unknown population parameters (like μ and σ) . A central tool for this is the normal curve, which is a specific, mathematically defined, bell-shaped, symmetrical, and unimodal frequency distribution. Its importance is highlighted by the Central Limit Theorem (CLT). The CLT states that as sample size increases, the distribution of sample means will approach a normal distribution, regardless of the original population&amp;rsquo;s shape.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Quantitative Research Methods</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-1/aqrm-2025-10-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 16:08:36 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/advanced-quantitative-research-methods/lecture-1/aqrm-2025-10-20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture introduces quantitative research as an objective, theory-driven approach that quantifies events into numerical data for statistical analysis. It contrasts with qualitative methods, which focus on interpreting social reality. A core component of this process is measurement: the assignment of numerals to objects or events according to rules. For a measure to be useful, it must be both reliable (consistent) and valid (accurately measuring what it intends to measure). Reliability is a necessary prerequisite for validity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Perception</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-3/cp-2025-10-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 17:02:14 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-3/cp-2025-10-15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perception is the complex process of organizing and interpreting sensory information to understand the environment, going beyond simple sensation, which is the initial neural response to physical energy. This interpretive process is challenging because the sensory information received by our receptors is often ambiguous. For instance, a single two-dimensional image on the retina could correspond to numerous three-dimensional objects in the world. Furthermore, objects can be partially hidden, blurred, or viewed from various angles, yet we can typically still identify them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Central Tendency and Variability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-2/stat-2025-10-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 14:49:31 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-2/stat-2025-10-14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Descriptive statistics provide a way to quantify and describe the basic characteristics of a data set. A fundamental aspect of this is identifying a single, representative value that best summarises the entire group of scores. This concept is known as central tendency, and it is measured in three primary ways: the mean, the median, and the mode.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mean represents the arithmetic average of all scores, calculated by summing the scores and dividing by the total number of scores. It acts as the mathematical balance point of the distribution but can be significantly influenced by extreme scores, or outliers. The mode is simply the most frequently occurring value in a data set. It is particularly useful for describing nominal variables. The median is the middle value when all scores are arranged in ascending order. Unlike the mean, the median is not affected by outliers, making it a more robust measure of central tendency for distributions that are skewed or contain extreme values. In a perfectly symmetrical, unimodal distribution, the mean, median, and mode will all be the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Cognitive Neuroscience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-2/cp-2025-10-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 14:34:45 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-2/cp-2025-10-08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The study of cognitive neuroscience begins with the brain&amp;rsquo;s fundamental unit, the neuron. Early theories imagined a continuous &amp;ldquo;nerve net,&amp;rdquo; but it was discovered that the nervous system is composed of individual cells. These neurons, with their distinct cell bodies, dendrites, and axons, transmit signals throughout the body. Communication between neurons occurs at the synapse, where an electrical impulse, or action potential, causes the release of chemical neurotransmitters that excite or inhibit the next neuron.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Measurement, Data, Distributions, Tables, and Graphs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-1/stat-2025-10-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 14:21:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/lecture-1/stat-2025-10-07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Statistics is a branch of mathematics focused on organizing, analyzing, and interpreting numerical data, primarily divided into two main areas. Descriptive statistics are used to summarize and make sense of a group of scores, while inferential statistics allow for drawing broader conclusions from the data collected in a study. Understanding statistics is crucial for conducting effective research, comprehending scientific literature, and developing critical thinking skills.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The foundation of statistical analysis begins with data, which are observations or measurements. A characteristic that can have different values is known as a variable, and a specific person&amp;rsquo;s value on that variable is a score. These variables can be measured on different scales, or levels of measurement. Nominal variables use categories or names, such as gender or ethnicity. Ordinal variables represent a rank order, like competition placements. Interval variables have equal intervals between values but lack a true zero, such as temperature in Celsius. Ratio variables possess all the properties of interval scales plus a true zero point, including measures like age, height, and income.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Cognitive Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-1/cp-2025-10-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 14:01:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-1/cp-2025-10-01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychology is the scientific study of mental processes, viewing the mind as a system that creates representations of the world to control functions like perception, attention, memory, and reasoning. The field&amp;rsquo;s roots are in philosophy, with thinkers like René Descartes proposing mind-body dualism and John Locke suggesting the mind is a &amp;ldquo;tabula rasa,&amp;rdquo; shaped by experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The scientific study began with Wilhelm Wundt&amp;rsquo;s structuralism, which aimed to identify the basic elements of consciousness through analytic introspection. This was followed by William James&amp;rsquo;s functionalism, which focused on how the mind helps individuals adapt to their environment. Gestalt psychology, founded by Max Wertheimer, shifted focus to how the mind organizes perceptions into meaningful wholes, asserting that the whole is more than the sum of its parts. However, the rise of behaviorism, championed by John B. Watson and B. F. Skinner, led to a period where psychology abandoned the study of the mind in favor of observable stimulus-response behaviors, analyzed through classical and operant conditioning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics Course Description and Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 13:47:11 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to the fundamental concepts of statistics in psychology, emphasizing data analysis and interpretation. Topics covered include data measurement, central tendency, variability, inferential statistics, hypothesis testing, t-tests, ANOVA, correlation, regression, and chi-square tests. Students will learn how to apply statistical techniques to psychological research, interpret results, and understand the importance of statistical significance, effect size, and power. This course provides essential skills for analyzing psychological data and conducting research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Process Course Description and Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 13:18:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course provides an overview of the fundamental processes involved in human cognition. Topics include perception, attention, memory, language, problem-solving, decision-making, and creativity. The course also explores cognitive neuroscience, conceptual knowledge, visual imagery, and human intelligence. Special focus is given to cognitive disorders, offering insights into how these processes can malfunction. Students will gain a deeper understanding of how the brain supports mental functions and how cognitive processes impact everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to your professor&#39;s blog!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 12:41:36 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m so excited to welcome you to my blog. Whether you’re looking for study materials, homework updates, or just a place to share ideas, this is where it’s all going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about this blog is that it’s going to help us stay organized and connected without drowning in a sea of emails. Instead of sending out a bunch of messages that might get lost in the inbox, I’ll be posting lecture summaries, homework assignments, important announcements, reminders, and updates right here. That way, you’ll always know where to look for the latest info, and we can avoid any confusion or missed messages. The blog is designed to make your life easier, so you can focus on learning and collaborating without the stress of keeping track of a million different things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
