<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 17:02:14 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Perception</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/week-3/cp-2025-10-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 17:02:14 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/week-3/cp-2025-10-15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perception is the complex process of organizing and interpreting sensory information to understand the environment, going beyond simple sensation, which is the initial neural response to physical energy. This interpretive process is challenging because the sensory information received by our receptors is often ambiguous. For instance, a single two-dimensional image on the retina could correspond to numerous three-dimensional objects in the world. Furthermore, objects can be partially hidden, blurred, or viewed from various angles, yet we can typically still identify them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Central Tendency and Variability</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/week-2/stat-2025-10-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2025 14:49:31 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/week-2/stat-2025-10-14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Descriptive statistics provide a way to quantify and describe the basic characteristics of a data set. A fundamental aspect of this is identifying a single, representative value that best summarises the entire group of scores. This concept is known as central tendency, and it is measured in three primary ways: the mean, the median, and the mode.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The mean represents the arithmetic average of all scores, calculated by summing the scores and dividing by the total number of scores. It acts as the mathematical balance point of the distribution but can be significantly influenced by extreme scores, or outliers. The mode is simply the most frequently occurring value in a data set. It is particularly useful for describing nominal variables. The median is the middle value when all scores are arranged in ascending order. Unlike the mean, the median is not affected by outliers, making it a more robust measure of central tendency for distributions that are skewed or contain extreme values. In a perfectly symmetrical, unimodal distribution, the mean, median, and mode will all be the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Cognitive Neuroscience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/week-2/cp-2025-10-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 14:34:45 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/week-2/cp-2025-10-08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The study of cognitive neuroscience begins with the brain&amp;rsquo;s fundamental unit, the neuron. Early theories imagined a continuous &amp;ldquo;nerve net,&amp;rdquo; but it was discovered that the nervous system is composed of individual cells. These neurons, with their distinct cell bodies, dendrites, and axons, transmit signals throughout the body. Communication between neurons occurs at the synapse, where an electrical impulse, or action potential, causes the release of chemical neurotransmitters that excite or inhibit the next neuron.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Measurement, Data, Distributions, Tables, and Graphs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/week-1/stat-2025-10-07/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 14:21:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/week-1/stat-2025-10-07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Statistics is a branch of mathematics focused on organizing, analyzing, and interpreting numerical data, primarily divided into two main areas. Descriptive statistics are used to summarize and make sense of a group of scores, while inferential statistics allow for drawing broader conclusions from the data collected in a study. Understanding statistics is crucial for conducting effective research, comprehending scientific literature, and developing critical thinking skills.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The foundation of statistical analysis begins with data, which are observations or measurements. A characteristic that can have different values is known as a variable, and a specific person&amp;rsquo;s value on that variable is a score. These variables can be measured on different scales, or levels of measurement. Nominal variables use categories or names, such as gender or ethnicity. Ordinal variables represent a rank order, like competition placements. Interval variables have equal intervals between values but lack a true zero, such as temperature in Celsius. Ratio variables possess all the properties of interval scales plus a true zero point, including measures like age, height, and income.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Cognitive Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/week-1/cp-2025-10-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 14:01:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/week-1/cp-2025-10-01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychology is the scientific study of mental processes, viewing the mind as a system that creates representations of the world to control functions like perception, attention, memory, and reasoning. The field&amp;rsquo;s roots are in philosophy, with thinkers like René Descartes proposing mind-body dualism and John Locke suggesting the mind is a &amp;ldquo;tabula rasa,&amp;rdquo; shaped by experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The scientific study began with Wilhelm Wundt&amp;rsquo;s structuralism, which aimed to identify the basic elements of consciousness through analytic introspection. This was followed by William James&amp;rsquo;s functionalism, which focused on how the mind helps individuals adapt to their environment. Gestalt psychology, founded by Max Wertheimer, shifted focus to how the mind organizes perceptions into meaningful wholes, asserting that the whole is more than the sum of its parts. However, the rise of behaviorism, championed by John B. Watson and B. F. Skinner, led to a period where psychology abandoned the study of the mind in favor of observable stimulus-response behaviors, analyzed through classical and operant conditioning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistics Course Description and Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 13:47:11 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course introduces students to the fundamental concepts of statistics in psychology, emphasizing data analysis and interpretation. Topics covered include data measurement, central tendency, variability, inferential statistics, hypothesis testing, t-tests, ANOVA, correlation, regression, and chi-square tests. Students will learn how to apply statistical techniques to psychological research, interpret results, and understand the importance of statistical significance, effect size, and power. This course provides essential skills for analyzing psychological data and conducting research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Process Course Description and Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 13:18:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course provides an overview of the fundamental processes involved in human cognition. Topics include perception, attention, memory, language, problem-solving, decision-making, and creativity. The course also explores cognitive neuroscience, conceptual knowledge, visual imagery, and human intelligence. Special focus is given to cognitive disorders, offering insights into how these processes can malfunction. Students will gain a deeper understanding of how the brain supports mental functions and how cognitive processes impact everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to your professor&#39;s blog!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 12:41:36 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m so excited to welcome you to my blog. Whether you’re looking for study materials, homework updates, or just a place to share ideas, this is where it’s all going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about this blog is that it’s going to help us stay organized and connected without drowning in a sea of emails. Instead of sending out a bunch of messages that might get lost in the inbox, I’ll be posting lecture summaries, homework assignments, important announcements, reminders, and updates right here. That way, you’ll always know where to look for the latest info, and we can avoid any confusion or missed messages. The blog is designed to make your life easier, so you can focus on learning and collaborating without the stress of keeping track of a million different things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
