<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 11:16:29 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MIDTERM: Social Psychology / MAN, PRMC</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/midterm/sp-nonpsy-midterm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 11:16:29 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/midterm/sp-nonpsy-midterm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;midterm-content&#34;&gt;Midterm Content:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 3: The Self &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 4: Social Cognition &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 5: Attitudes &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 6: Persuasion &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 7: Groups&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIDTERM: Social Psychology / PCG, PCG (NP), PSY, PSY (NP)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/midterm/sp-psy-midterm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:48:40 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/midterm/sp-psy-midterm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;midterm-content&#34;&gt;Midterm Content:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 3: The Self &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 4: Social Cognition &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 5: Attitudes &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 6: Persuasion &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 7: Groups&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MIDTERM: Computer Aided Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/midterm/cae-midterm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:28:34 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/midterm/cae-midterm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;midterm-project-content&#34;&gt;Midterm Project Content:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LECTURE 1: Introduction to Computer Aided Education &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 2: Computers, Interactions, and Learning &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 3: Communication Styles &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 4: Types of Computer-Based Material &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 5: Assessment Methods &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 6: Text &lt;br&gt;&#xA;LECTURE 7: Color&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;midterm-project-upload&#34;&gt;Midterm Project Upload:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can access and submit your midterm project at the following &lt;a href=&#34;https://forms.office.com/Pages/ResponsePage.aspx?id=_FqJ5k4h7EOVfcOhjK4agRQtemblazZMjLRNMzJCeQ9UMzlLQVZMNFM0OFZEVzBIV0tIRlVLMVVSRy4u&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;LINK&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;The deadline for submission is 11 April, 15:15.&lt;/strong&gt; Once the deadline has passed, the system will no longer accept any additional submissions. The allowed maximum file size is 100 Mb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Professional Competence and Training</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-7/week-7-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:11:32 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-7/week-7-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Professional competence in the humanities and social sciences is both an ethical and legal duty, rooted in the principles of beneficence and non-maleficence. Inadequate competence can result in client harm and legal consequences. Ethical practice demands self-awareness, continuous self-evaluation, and a commitment to lifelong learning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Professional guidelines from organizations such as ACA, APA, and NASW emphasize practicing within one’s scope, cultural competence, and the importance of supervision and consultation. However, defining the limits of competence and minimum qualifications remains a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Groups</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-7/week-7-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:04:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-7/week-7-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Groups are defined as two or more individuals who interact and influence each other, often driven by shared goals and interdependence. People join groups for evolutionary advantages, goal achievement, identity formation, and adherence to social norms. Groups typically consist of three to six members and are shaped by social norms and roles, which guide behavior but can also lead to identity loss when roles are overly internalized.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Group cohesiveness fosters member retention and participation but may hinder performance if harmony is prioritized over effective solutions. While similarity enhances cohesiveness, diversity—across race, experience, and attitudes—can improve group performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Groups</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-7/week-7-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 09:44:14 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-7/week-7-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A group is defined as two or more individuals who interact and influence each other, often forming around shared goals, needs, or identities. Evolutionarily, groups enhanced survival by facilitating cooperation in tasks like hunting and caregiving. They also provide social norms and roles that guide behavior, though these can sometimes suppress individuality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Groups typically consist of three to six members and are shaped by norms, roles, cohesiveness, and diversity. While cohesiveness strengthens bonds, it can hinder performance if harmony is prioritized over effective decision-making. Diversity, especially in race and experience, can enhance group outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Color</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-7/week-7-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 09:29:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-7/week-7-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on the role of color in computer-aided education, emphasizing its impact on user engagement, comprehension, and interface design. Color is defined through three variables: hue, saturation, and intensity. Computers use the RGB model to generate colors, and effective use of color can attract attention, reinforce key points, and organize information.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Color must be applied systematically to support learning objectives. Random or excessive use can distract or confuse learners. Consistency in color usage helps users develop a visual code, improving navigation and understanding. Designers are advised to limit the number of colors, maintain high contrast for readability, and consider color blindness by testing interfaces in monochrome. Cultural differences influence color perception, making audience testing essential. Specific colors carry common associations—red for danger, green for calm—but these meanings vary. Highlighting with color, especially when combined with graphics or layout elements, enhances clarity and focus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Persuasion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-6/week-6-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 15:07:39 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-6/week-6-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on persuasion explored various facets of persuasive communication and its impact on attitude change. Persuasion involves messages aimed at altering attitudes and behaviors, with key elements including the communicator, the message, the medium, and audience characteristics. The lecture highlighted the third-person effect, where individuals believe they are less influenced by advertisements than others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attitude change often results from social influence and persuasive communication, with emotional and cognitive appeals playing significant roles. Fear appeals are effective when paired with solutions, while advertising leverages affective and cognitive appeals based on cultural contexts. The lecture also discussed self-generated persuasion, where individuals change attitudes by generating their own arguments, and cognitive dissonance, which occurs when actions contradict beliefs, prompting attitude alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Persuasion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-6/week-6-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 15:00:20 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-6/week-6-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on persuasion explored various facets of persuasive communication and its impact on attitude change. Persuasion involves messages aimed at altering attitudes and behaviors, with key elements including the communicator, the message, the medium, and audience characteristics. The lecture highlighted the third-person effect, where individuals believe they are less influenced by advertisements than others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attitude change often results from social influence and persuasive communication, with emotional and cognitive appeals playing significant roles. Fear appeals are effective when paired with solutions, while advertising leverages affective and cognitive appeals based on cultural contexts. The lecture also discussed self-generated persuasion, where individuals change attitudes by generating their own arguments, and cognitive dissonance, which occurs when actions contradict beliefs, prompting attitude alignment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Text</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-6/week-6-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:50:32 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-6/week-6-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture emphasizes the significance of text in computer-based learning, despite the rise of multimedia. Text remains a powerful communication tool, though presenting it on screens differs from traditional print due to lower resolution and landscape orientation. Reading on screens is slower and less comfortable than on paper, necessitating careful design of digital text.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Effective computer-based learning materials should include clear headings, subheadings, and navigation clues, guiding learners through the content. Instructions should outline learning objectives and provide study guidance. An informal, friendly communication style is recommended, using plain language and avoiding jargon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURES 5 and 6 (Self-study)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-5-6/week-5-6-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:15:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-5-6/week-5-6-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lectures-for-self-study&#34;&gt;Lectures for self-study:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidentiality: Ethical and Legal Issues (WEEK 5)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter covers the essential aspects of maintaining confidentiality within professional environments, highlighting both ethical considerations and legal obligations. Understanding these principles is crucial for your future roles.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing Boundaries and Multiple Relationships (WEEK 6)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This section addresses the complexities of maintaining professional boundaries and handling multiple relationships. It provides guidance on avoiding conflicts of interest and ensuring ethical interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Attitudes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-5/week-5-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 13:59:24 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-5/week-5-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on attitudes in social psychology explored the origins, components, and influences on attitudes. Attitudes are evaluations of people, objects, and ideas, shaped by genetics and social experiences. They consist of cognitive, affective, and behavioral components. Cognitively based attitudes rely on beliefs about an object, while affectively based attitudes stem from feelings and values, often influenced by conditioning. Behaviorally based attitudes are derived from observing one&amp;rsquo;s behavior toward an object, as explained by self-perception theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Attitudes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-5/week-5-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 13:33:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-5/week-5-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attitudes are evaluations of people, objects, and ideas, shaped by genetics and social experiences. They have three components: cognitive (based on beliefs), affective (rooted in emotions and values), and behavioral (inferred from actions). Attitudes can be explicit (consciously endorsed) or implicit (unconscious and shaped by early experiences).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Their influence on behavior depends on accessibility and context. Spontaneous actions align with strong, readily available attitudes, while deliberate behavior follows the Theory of Planned Behavior, which considers specific attitudes, social norms, and perceived control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Assessment Methods</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-5/week-5-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 13:21:19 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-5/week-5-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Computer-aided education (CAE) employs digital tools for assessment, providing objective, cost-effective alternatives to traditional methods. Assessments in CAE serve not only to measure learning but also to reinforce knowledge and encourage self-reflection.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pre-tests help customize learning by identifying prior knowledge and learning styles, while post-tests evaluate progress and suggest remedial actions. Adaptive testing adjusts difficulty based on responses, tailoring the experience to individual learners. Feedback is crucial, offering explanations, praise, and corrective guidance to enhance understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Client Rights and Counselor Responsibilities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-4/week-4-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 12:05:48 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-4/week-4-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on the ethical, legal, and professional responsibilities of counselors, emphasizing the importance of client rights. Central to ethical practice is the concept of informed consent, which allows clients to make autonomous decisions about their therapy. This process involves providing clients with comprehensive information about therapy goals, risks, benefits, and procedures, thereby enhancing the therapeutic alliance and minimizing misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Informed consent is not a one-time event but an ongoing process that requires regular updates and check-ins to empower clients and maintain a collaborative partnership. Legal aspects of informed consent demand that clients understand the information, give consent voluntarily, and are competent to do so. Documentation of informed consent is crucial for legal protection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Social Cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-4/week-4-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 12:01:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-4/week-4-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social cognition explored how individuals perceive and interpret the social world. It highlighted the distinction between automatic and controlled thinking. Automatic thinking is non-conscious, effortless, and involves the use of schemas—mental structures that help organize social information. These schemas are influenced by culture and can be primed by recent experiences, affecting judgments and decisions. The lecture also discussed the self-fulfilling prophecy, where expectations about others can influence their behavior, making those expectations come true.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Social Cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-4/week-4-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 11:43:17 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-4/week-4-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social cognition explored how individuals perceive and interpret the social world. It highlighted the distinction between automatic and controlled thinking. Automatic thinking is non-conscious, effortless, and involves the use of schemas—mental structures that help organize social information. These schemas are influenced by culture and can be primed by recent experiences, affecting judgments and decisions. The lecture also discussed the self-fulfilling prophecy, where expectations about others can influence their behavior, making those expectations come true.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Types of Computer-Based Material</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-4/week-4-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 11:02:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-4/week-4-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on various types of computer-based learning materials. It highlighted the diversity of these materials, which depend on the design strategy, medium, and delivery approach. Key types include computer-based training (CBT), computer-managed learning (CML), integrated learning systems (ILS), intelligent tutoring systems (ITS), electronic performance support systems (EPSS), and computer-aided assessment (CAA).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CBT is characterized by a tutorial approach, presenting content through frames of text and graphics, with learner responses guiding the progression. CML involves managing learning activities, assessments, and administration, with different perspectives for tutors, students, administrators, and technicians. ILS combines extensive learning materials with a management system to tailor content to individual learners&amp;rsquo; abilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Values and the Helping Relationship</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-3/week-3-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:54:18 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-3/week-3-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In counseling, values significantly shape the therapeutic process. Counselors must be conscious of their own values and avoid imposing personal beliefs on clients, adhering to ethical guidelines that emphasize cultural awareness in value formation. The debate between objectivity and value neutrality highlights that values inevitably influence counseling relationships, affecting various aspects. Ethical responsibility requires counselors to monitor how they communicate values, considering power dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Value imposition occurs when counselors attempt to influence clients to adopt their values, either actively or passively. Ethical codes, such as those from the ACA and ASCA, caution against this practice. When facing value conflicts, counselors should not refer clients merely due to disagreements but only when lacking necessary skills. Referrals should be based on self-awareness of competence limitations, prioritizing client needs over personal beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: The Self</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-3/week-3-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:52:39 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-3/week-3-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explored the concept of self, focusing on self-concept, self-awareness, and self-perception. Self-concept is defined as the beliefs individuals hold about their personal attributes, with self-schema acting as a cognitive framework guiding perception and evaluation. The development of self-concept begins in early childhood, with human self-recognition emerging between 18-24 months. Cultural influences shape self-concept, with independent and interdependent views of self highlighting differences in self-definition based on personal attributes versus relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: The Self</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-3/week-3-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:34:06 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-3/week-3-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explored the concept of self, focusing on self-concept, self-awareness, and self-perception. Self-concept is defined as the beliefs individuals hold about their personal attributes, with self-schema acting as a cognitive framework guiding perception and evaluation. The development of self-concept begins in early childhood, with human self-recognition emerging between 18-24 months. Cultural influences shape self-concept, with independent and interdependent views of self highlighting differences in self-definition based on personal attributes versus relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Communication Styles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-3/week-3-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:28:49 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-3/week-3-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on the role of Graphical User Interfaces (GUIs) in modern computing, emphasizing their visual interaction through windows, icons, and menus. It highlighted the importance of informing learners about the nature of their educational experience and outlined key components for building effective computer learning materials, such as introductions, study time advice, and context-sensitive help.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture compared computer-based learning (CBL) with traditional educational approaches, noting that CBL offers individualized instruction and flexible learning environments, unlike the one-to-many communication in traditional settings. CBL allows for one-to-one communication and varied media use, providing a more interactive and personalized learning experience. It also reduces costs as the number of students increases, unlike traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: The Counselor as a Person and as a Professional</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-2/week-2-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:16:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-2/week-2-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Self-awareness is crucial for therapists to maintain ethical practice, as a lack of it can hinder client progress and shift focus from client needs to therapist inadequacies. Therapists must recognize their personal needs, unresolved issues, and vulnerabilities. Many counselors are motivated by their own life struggles, but their needs should not overshadow client growth. It&amp;rsquo;s unrealistic to expect therapists to have resolved all personal issues; the key is how they manage them. Personal therapy offers therapists insight into client experiences, promotes self-care, and enhances empathy and competence. Graduate clinicians who undergo personal therapy develop stronger therapeutic alliances and gain valuable insights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-2/week-2-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-2/week-2-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social psychology explored various questions about human behavior and social interactions, such as how people perceive and reason about the social world, the dynamics of group membership, factors influencing aggression and prejudice, and the reasons behind interpersonal attraction and cooperation. It also examined the effectiveness of political advertisements and the motivations for helping behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address these questions, the lecture emphasized the importance of the scientific method, which involves generating hypotheses, testing them, and communicating findings. It distinguished between science, pseudoscience, protoscience, and nonscience, highlighting the need for falsifiability in scientific hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-2/week-2-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:08 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-2/week-2-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social psychology explored various questions about human behavior and social interactions, such as how people perceive and reason about the social world, the dynamics of group membership, factors influencing aggression and prejudice, and the reasons behind interpersonal attraction and cooperation. It also examined the effectiveness of political advertisements and the motivations for helping behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address these questions, the lecture emphasized the importance of the scientific method, which involves generating hypotheses, testing them, and communicating findings. It distinguished between science, pseudoscience, protoscience, and nonscience, highlighting the need for falsifiability in scientific hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Computers, Interactions, and Learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-2/week-2-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-2/week-2-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A computer is a programmable device capable of storing, retrieving, and processing data based on instructions. Its key components include storage devices like RAM and hard disks, and the CPU, which controls other parts of the computer. Learning is defined as acquiring knowledge or skills through experience, study, or teaching, resulting in relatively permanent changes. Various learning approaches include the behavioral, cognitive, and constructivist methods, each emphasizing different aspects of the learning process.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Professional Ethics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-1/week-1-elpihss-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:52 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/ethical-legal-and-professional-issues-in-humanities-and-social-sciences/week-1/week-1-elpihss-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explores ethics, a philosophical branch examining moral judgments and their nature, divided into subfields like normative, applied, metaethics, and descriptive ethics. Professional ethics dictate acceptable conduct within professions, often guided by a code of ethics. These codes provide guidelines for ethical conduct, decision-making, and professional behavior, ensuring accountability and client welfare. Ethical dilemmas, such as confidentiality versus the duty to warn, illustrate the challenges faced by professionals. Common themes in ethics codes include client welfare, competence, cultural respect, and confidentiality. However, these codes have limitations, being broad and sometimes conflicting with laws or cultural norms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-1/week-1-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-1/week-1-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture treated the profound effects of social influence and isolation on human behavior and cognition. It highlighted a study involving nine polar expeditioners in Antarctica, revealing significant reductions in the volume of the dentate gyrus due to social isolation, underscoring the brain&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability to such conditions. The lecture also examined the tragic events of the Jonestown massacre, illustrating the extreme power of social influence under cult leader Jim Jones, where 914 individuals perished after being coerced into a mass suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-1/week-1-sp-psy-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:35 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-pcg-psy/week-1/week-1-sp-psy-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture treated the profound effects of social influence and isolation on human behavior and cognition. It highlighted a study involving nine polar expeditioners in Antarctica, revealing significant reductions in the volume of the dentate gyrus due to social isolation, underscoring the brain&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability to such conditions. The lecture also examined the tragic events of the Jonestown massacre, illustrating the extreme power of social influence under cult leader Jim Jones, where 914 individuals perished after being coerced into a mass suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Computer Aided Education</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-1/week-1-cae-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:25 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/computer-aided-education/week-1/week-1-cae-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Computer Aided Education introductory lecture explored the integration of computers into the educational process. The lecture began by defining key terms: computer, aided, and education. It then posed critical questions about the role of computers in enhancing learning, their potential to increase student interest, and whether they could replace teachers. The discussion also considered the future importance of digital literacy compared to traditional literacy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture covered various aspects of computer-aided education, including interaction and learning, communication styles, and types of computer-based learning materials. It looked into assessment methods and the use of text, color, graphics, multimedia, online learning, and networking. Content and layout design were emphasized, along with using computers for research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to your professor&#39;s blog!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 13:56:27 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/general-discussion/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’m so excited to welcome you to my blog. Whether you’re looking for study materials, homework updates, or just a place to share ideas, this is where it’s all going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the best things about this blog is that it’s going to help us stay organized and connected without drowning in a sea of emails. Instead of sending out a bunch of messages that might get lost in the inbox, I’ll be posting lecture summaries, homework assignments, important announcements, reminders, and updates right here. That way, you’ll always know where to look for the latest info, and we can avoid any confusion or missed messages. The blog is designed to make your life easier, so you can focus on learning and collaborating without the stress of keeping track of a million different things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
