<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Psychology / MAN, PRMC on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/social-psychology-/-man-prmc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Psychology / MAN, PRMC on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 12:01:12 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/social-psychology-/-man-prmc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Social Cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-4/week-4-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 12:01:12 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-4/week-4-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social cognition explored how individuals perceive and interpret the social world. It highlighted the distinction between automatic and controlled thinking. Automatic thinking is non-conscious, effortless, and involves the use of schemas—mental structures that help organize social information. These schemas are influenced by culture and can be primed by recent experiences, affecting judgments and decisions. The lecture also discussed the self-fulfilling prophecy, where expectations about others can influence their behavior, making those expectations come true.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: The Self</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-3/week-3-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 17:52:39 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-3/week-3-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture explored the concept of self, focusing on self-concept, self-awareness, and self-perception. Self-concept is defined as the beliefs individuals hold about their personal attributes, with self-schema acting as a cognitive framework guiding perception and evaluation. The development of self-concept begins in early childhood, with human self-recognition emerging between 18-24 months. Cultural influences shape self-concept, with independent and interdependent views of self highlighting differences in self-definition based on personal attributes versus relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Methodology to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-2/week-2-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:50:16 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-2/week-2-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture on social psychology explored various questions about human behavior and social interactions, such as how people perceive and reason about the social world, the dynamics of group membership, factors influencing aggression and prejudice, and the reasons behind interpersonal attraction and cooperation. It also examined the effectiveness of political advertisements and the motivations for helping behavior.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address these questions, the lecture emphasized the importance of the scientific method, which involves generating hypotheses, testing them, and communicating findings. It distinguished between science, pseudoscience, protoscience, and nonscience, highlighting the need for falsifiability in scientific hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Social Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-1/week-1-sp-man-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 16:49:43 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/social-psychology-man-prmc/week-1/week-1-sp-man-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture treated the profound effects of social influence and isolation on human behavior and cognition. It highlighted a study involving nine polar expeditioners in Antarctica, revealing significant reductions in the volume of the dentate gyrus due to social isolation, underscoring the brain&amp;rsquo;s vulnerability to such conditions. The lecture also examined the tragic events of the Jonestown massacre, illustrating the extreme power of social influence under cult leader Jim Jones, where 914 individuals perished after being coerced into a mass suicide.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
