<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cognitive Process on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/cognitive-process/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cognitive Process on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 13:40:03 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/cognitive-process/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Memory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-5/cp-post-lecture-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 13:40:03 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-5/cp-post-lecture-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture focused on memory processes within cognitive psychology, examining models, types, and key experiments. The Modal Model of Memory, by Atkinson and Shiffrin, introduces three stages: sensory memory, which briefly holds all incoming sensory input; short-term memory (STM), retaining small bits for about 15-20 seconds; and long-term memory (LTM), storing extensive information over years.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;STM was explored through experiments by Peterson and Peterson, who demonstrated STM’s limited duration and reliance on rehearsal, and by George Miller, who proposed its capacity as 5-9 items. Techniques like chunking were shown to extend STM’s capacity, while Luck and Vogel’s change detection method suggested STM’s retention of about four items. Working memory, distinct from STM, involves holding and manipulating information for complex tasks. Baddeley’s model includes the phonological loop for verbal data, the visuospatial sketchpad for spatial data, and the central executive for coordination. Later, the episodic buffer was added as a storage that interacts with LTM. Episodic and semantic memory are differentiated within LTM; episodic enables mental time travel to past experiences, while semantic involves general knowledge without specific recall. Studies on priming and procedural memory reveal the influence of implicit memory on behavior, even without conscious recall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Attention</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-4/cp-post-lecture-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 12:37:44 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-4/cp-post-lecture-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Attention, a key cognitive process, is essential for selecting and focusing on specific stimuli. William James described attention as the mind’s process of vividly highlighting certain elements while filtering others. Broadbent’s Filter Model emphasized that attention filters input based on physical characteristics, while Treisman modified this to suggest a more flexible approach, allowing some unattended information through if it’s significant, such as one’s name (the “cocktail party effect”). Later models proposed that attention could also occur at a later processing stage, selecting information by meaning. Processing capacity and perceptual load influence attention’s effectiveness; easier tasks allow for more distraction processing, while complex tasks limit this. Load Theory posits that high-load tasks consume all cognitive resources, reducing susceptibility to distractions, as shown in the Stroop Effect and Lavie’s work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Perception</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-3/cp-post-lecture-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 20:02:06 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-3/cp-post-lecture-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perception is the process by which the brain organizes and interprets sensory signals, enabling us to interact with our environment. It starts with sensation, where physical energy stimulates receptor cells, but perception involves interpreting these signals to understand shapes, objects, and events. Perception is influenced by both bottom-up processing, which begins with stimuli received by sensory organs, and top-down processing, shaped by prior knowledge and expectations. Challenges in perception arise due to the ambiguous nature of stimuli. Objects may be hidden, blurred, or viewed from different angles, making perception complex. Humans use unconscious inference, as proposed by Helmholtz, to perceive the most likely scenario based on sensory input. Gestalt principles such as proximity, similarity, and good continuation help organize visual information into coherent forms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Cognitive Neuroscience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-2/cp-post-lecture-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 17:40:22 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-2/cp-post-lecture-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The human brain contains approximately 86 billion neurons, each connected to thousands of others via synapses. Neurons come in various types, including sensory, motor, and interneurons. Sensory neurons transmit signals from sensory organs to the brain, while motor neurons control movement. Interneurons facilitate communication between other neurons. The central nervous system (CNS) comprises the brain and spinal cord, while the peripheral nervous system (PNS) connects the body’s organs and limbs to the CNS. The PNS is divided into the autonomic nervous system (ANS), controlling involuntary functions like digestion, and the sensory-somatic nervous system (SSNS), which manages voluntary movements and sensory information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Cognitive Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-1/cp-post-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 13:48:30 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-1/cp-post-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychology focuses on understanding mental processes and how the mind operates. It studies how the brain processes information, creates representations of the world, and helps us interact with it to achieve our goals. Cognitive psychology investigates processes like perception, memory, attention, language, reasoning, and decision-making. The brain is central to this, with its 86 billion neurons forming intricate connections. Cognitive processes are examined at three levels: the brain (physical structures and neural activity), the person (mental functions), and the group (social and cultural influences).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Cognitive Process&#39; Course Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 20:38:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course provides an overview of the fundamental processes involved in human cognition. Topics include perception, attention, memory, language, problem-solving, decision-making, and creativity. The course also explores cognitive neuroscience, conceptual knowledge, visual imagery, and human intelligence. Special focus is given to cognitive disorders, offering insights into how these processes can malfunction. Students will gain a deeper understanding of how the brain supports mental functions and how cognitive processes impact everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
