<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cognitive Process on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/cognitive-process/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cognitive Process on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 11:15:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/cognitive-process/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 11: Human Intelligence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-11/cp-2025-12-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-11/cp-2025-12-17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intelligence is defined as the capacity to learn from experience and adapt to the surrounding environment, integrating various cognitive processes such as attention, memory, and reasoning. Historically, measurement approaches evolved from Francis Galton’s psychophysical methods to Alfred Binet’s judgmental approach, which focused on academic learning and higher-level judgment. This led to the development of the Intelligence Quotient (IQ), transitioning from William Stern’s ratio-based formula to the modern deviation IQ, which utilizes a normal distribution bell curve with an average score of 100. Contemporary assessment is primarily conducted through the Stanford-Binet and Wechsler scales, which evaluate domains like fluid reasoning, verbal comprehension, and processing speed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 10: Judgement, Decisions, and Reasoning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-10/cp-2025-12-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-10/cp-2025-12-10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Human thinking consists of complex cognitive processes including judgment, reasoning, and decision-making. Judgment involves forming evaluations based on observations, while reasoning represents the process of drawing conclusions from evidence. Decision-making serves as the final selection between alternatives, relying heavily on the preceding judgmental and reasoning stages. These processes are inherently interconnected and often rely on dual systems: the fast, intuitive System 1 and the slow, analytical System 2.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Inductive reasoning draws general conclusions from specific observations. The strength of such arguments is determined by the number, quality, and representativeness of the evidence. Because this reasoning is probabilistic rather than definite, humans often employ heuristics, or mental shortcuts. The availability heuristic leads individuals to judge the probability of events based on how easily they can be recalled from memory, often influenced by media salience or emotional charge. The representativeness heuristic causes people to categorize instances based on how well they match a stereotype, frequently leading to base rate neglect or violations of the conjunction rule. Additional cognitive biases, such as confirmation bias, the myside bias, and the backfire effect, further complicate inductive judgments by causing individuals to favor information that supports prior beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 9: Problem Solving and Creativity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-09/cp-2025-12-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-09/cp-2025-12-03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychologists define a problem as a situation where an obstacle exists between a present state and a goal state, necessitating specific actions to bridge the gap. The Gestalt approach emphasizes that success depends heavily on how a problem is represented in the mind, often requiring a process of restructuring or reorganizing that representation. This restructuring facilitates insight, a sudden realization or &amp;ldquo;Aha!&amp;rdquo; experience that differs fundamentally from the gradual, step-by-step progress seen in analytical or non-insight problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IN-CLASS PRESENTATIONS: Cognitive Process</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/activity/in-class-presentations-cognitive-process/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 22:39:13 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/statistics/activity/in-class-presentations-cognitive-process/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;instructions&#34;&gt;Instructions:&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;step-1-choose-an-article&#34;&gt;Step 1: Choose an Article&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Go to Google Scholar. Find a full-text peer-reviewed, empirical research article (one that collects actual data, not a literature review or meta-analysis) on a topic that interests you. Tip: Don’t pick a 50-page paper with six different experiments. Pick a standard paper with a clear, singular focus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h4 id=&#34;step-2-the--structure&#34;&gt;Step 2: The  Structure&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You only have 3 minutes. That means you cannot read the abstract to us. You must extract the core narrative. Structure your talk using these five specific pillars:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 8: Language</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-08/cp-2025-11-26/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-08/cp-2025-11-26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Human language is defined as a system of communication utilizing sounds or symbols to express feelings, thoughts, ideas, and experiences. Its defining characteristic is creativity, which stems from a structure that is both hierarchical and rule-based, allowing for the generation of unique sequences. Psycholinguistics examines the psychological processes behind this ability, breaking language down into phonology (sounds), syntax (structure), semantics (meaning), and pragmatics (implied meaning).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the lexical level, word frequency heavily influences processing speed, with high-frequency words eliciting faster responses than low-frequency ones. Readers must also navigate lexical ambiguity, where context and meaning dominance help select the correct interpretation of multi-meaning words. When combining words into sentences, the mind engages in parsing. The Garden Path Model suggests this is done via heuristics like late closure, while the constraint-based approach argues that syntax, semantics, and context serve as simultaneous constraints to guide understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 7: Visual Imagery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-07/cp-2025-11-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-07/cp-2025-11-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Visual imagery is defined as the ability to recreate the sensory world in the absence of physical stimuli, a capacity that extends beyond vision to include taste, smell, and touch. Historically, the study of imagery fluctuated, moving from Wundt’s view that images are essential to thought, through the &amp;ldquo;imageless thought&amp;rdquo; debate and Behaviorist rejection, before being revived during the Cognitive Revolution. Alan Paivio’s work on the conceptual peg hypothesis later demonstrated that concrete nouns create mental anchors, making them easier to remember than abstract concepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 6: Conceptual Knowledge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-06/cp-2025-11-05/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-06/cp-2025-11-05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture examines conceptual knowledge, the system that enables people to recognize objects and make inferences about their properties. This knowledge is organized into concepts (mental representations, like &amp;ldquo;cat&amp;rdquo;) and categories (groups of objects, like &amp;ldquo;furniture&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Early attempts to categorize using rigid definitions (the definitional approach) were found to be inadequate, as many category members (like different types of chairs) do not meet all criteria. This led to the &lt;strong&gt;Prototype Approach&lt;/strong&gt;, which posits that categories are formed around a single &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; member, or prototype. New items are judged based on their &amp;ldquo;typicality,&amp;rdquo; or resemblance to this prototype. This explains the &amp;ldquo;typicality effect,&amp;rdquo; where highly typical objects (like &amp;ldquo;sparrow&amp;rdquo; for &amp;ldquo;bird&amp;rdquo;) are verified more rapidly than atypical ones (like &amp;ldquo;penguin&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Memory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-05/cp-2025-10-29/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-05/cp-2025-10-29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Memory is the process of retaining, retrieving, and using information after the original stimulus is gone. The classic Modal Model of Memory breaks this process into three structural stages. First, Sensory Memory briefly holds all incoming sensory information for less than a second. Sperling&amp;rsquo;s partial report experiments demonstrated that while sensory memory has a large capacity, the information fades rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Information attended to moves into Short-Term Memory (STM), a store with a limited duration and capacity. Without rehearsal, information in STM lasts only about 15-20 seconds. While traditionally thought to hold &amp;ldquo;seven plus or minus two&amp;rdquo; items, modern change detection studies suggest the capacity is closer to four items. This capacity is also affected by information complexity, not just item count. However, capacity can be expanded by chunking—grouping small units into larger, meaningful ones. The concept of STM was refined into Working Memory (WM), which is not just a passive store, but an active system for manipulating information for complex tasks. This multi-component model includes the Phonological Loop for verbal and auditory information and the Visuospatial Sketch Pad for visual and spatial information. These &amp;ldquo;slave systems&amp;rdquo; are coordinated by the Central Executive, which directs attention.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Attention</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-04/cp-2025-10-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-04/cp-2025-10-22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture defines attention as the mind taking possession of one object or train of thought, implying a withdrawal from some things to deal effectively with others. This process manifests as selective attention (focusing), divided attention (multitasking), and attentional capture. Early models sought to explain when selection occurs. Broadbent&amp;rsquo;s filter model proposed an early filter based on physical characteristics, blocking unattended information. However, this was challenged by the &amp;ldquo;cocktail party effect&amp;rdquo; (hearing one&amp;rsquo;s name) and findings that meaning could be processed from an unattended ear. Treisman’s attenuation model modified this, suggesting the unattended message is weakened, not blocked, allowing salient information (like one&amp;rsquo;s name) to pass. In contrast, late selection models proposed that all stimuli are processed for meaning before selection. The Load Theory of Attention addresses how we ignore distractions, positing that this depends on the task&amp;rsquo;s perceptual load. Low-load (easy) tasks leave spare processing capacity that &amp;ldquo;spills over&amp;rdquo; to process distractors, making distraction more likely. High-load (hard) tasks consume all resources, leaving none to process distractors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Perception</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-03/cp-2025-10-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-03/cp-2025-10-15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perception is the complex process of organizing and interpreting sensory information to understand the environment, going beyond simple sensation, which is the initial neural response to physical energy. This interpretive process is challenging because the sensory information received by our receptors is often ambiguous. For instance, a single two-dimensional image on the retina could correspond to numerous three-dimensional objects in the world. Furthermore, objects can be partially hidden, blurred, or viewed from various angles, yet we can typically still identify them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Cognitive Neuroscience</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-02/cp-2025-10-08/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-02/cp-2025-10-08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The study of cognitive neuroscience begins with the brain&amp;rsquo;s fundamental unit, the neuron. Early theories imagined a continuous &amp;ldquo;nerve net,&amp;rdquo; but it was discovered that the nervous system is composed of individual cells. These neurons, with their distinct cell bodies, dendrites, and axons, transmit signals throughout the body. Communication between neurons occurs at the synapse, where an electrical impulse, or action potential, causes the release of chemical neurotransmitters that excite or inhibit the next neuron.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Introduction to Cognitive Psychology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-01/cp-2025-10-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/lecture-01/cp-2025-10-01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychology is the scientific study of mental processes, viewing the mind as a system that creates representations of the world to control functions like perception, attention, memory, and reasoning. The field&amp;rsquo;s roots are in philosophy, with thinkers like René Descartes proposing mind-body dualism and John Locke suggesting the mind is a &amp;ldquo;tabula rasa,&amp;rdquo; shaped by experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The scientific study began with Wilhelm Wundt&amp;rsquo;s structuralism, which aimed to identify the basic elements of consciousness through analytic introspection. This was followed by William James&amp;rsquo;s functionalism, which focused on how the mind helps individuals adapt to their environment. Gestalt psychology, founded by Max Wertheimer, shifted focus to how the mind organizes perceptions into meaningful wholes, asserting that the whole is more than the sum of its parts. However, the rise of behaviorism, championed by John B. Watson and B. F. Skinner, led to a period where psychology abandoned the study of the mind in favor of observable stimulus-response behaviors, analyzed through classical and operant conditioning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Process Course Description and Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 11:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/cognitive-process/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course provides an overview of the fundamental processes involved in human cognition. Topics include perception, attention, memory, language, problem-solving, decision-making, and creativity. The course also explores cognitive neuroscience, conceptual knowledge, visual imagery, and human intelligence. Special focus is given to cognitive disorders, offering insights into how these processes can malfunction. Students will gain a deeper understanding of how the brain supports mental functions and how cognitive processes impact everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
