<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Introduction to Psychology on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/introduction-to-psychology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Introduction to Psychology on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 21:36:09 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/introduction-to-psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 5: Memory and Cognition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-5/itp-post-lecture-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 21:36:09 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-5/itp-post-lecture-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Cognitive psychology rose to prominence in the 1960s, largely influenced by the computer model, which likened the human mind to a system for data input, processing, storage, and retrieval. Key concepts include memory, the ability to store and recall information, and cognition, which is the process of acquiring and utilizing knowledge. Memory plays a vital role in daily life, from simple tasks like recalling names to complex skills like programming. However, memory is not a flawless record of past experiences. Instead, it is reconstructive, piecing information together through perceptions, emotions, and beliefs, which can introduce errors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 4: Learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-4/itp-post-lecture-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 11:03:47 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-4/itp-post-lecture-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lecture introduces the concept of learning, defined as acquiring lasting knowledge or behaviors through experience. It contrasts innate behavior with learned behavior, emphasizing that most behaviors are a mix of both. Two main types of learning are discussed: associative and nonassociative. Associative learning, such as classical conditioning, involves linking one stimulus with another, demonstrated by Pavlov’s dog experiments. Phases of classical conditioning, including acquisition, extinction, and spontaneous recovery, illustrate how conditioned responses develop and fade over time. Nonassociative learning includes habituation and sensitization, where reactions to a stimulus either decrease or increase with repeated exposure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 3: Sensation and Perception</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-3/itp-post-lecture-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 11:25:38 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-3/itp-post-lecture-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lecture on sensation and perception covered the processes that enable us to sense and interpret our environment. Sensation involves detecting physical energy through receptor cells before the brain organizes and interprets it. Perception is the neural process of organizing sensory input into coherent units, identifying objects and locations. We explored various senses beyond sight, including balance, body position, pain, and temperature. Psychophysics was introduced, discussing thresholds for detecting stimuli and how subliminal messaging works. Signal Detection Theory explained how people discern signals amid noise, highlighting sensitivity and bias.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 2: Brain and Behavior</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-2/itp-post-lecture-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 19:46:02 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-2/itp-post-lecture-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The brain consists of around 86 billion neurons, each forming thousands of connections, enabling rapid transmission of electrical signals. Neurons, the brain’s fundamental units, receive and send information through a complex network. Early theories proposed continuous neural networks, but later discoveries by Golgi and Cajal revealed that neurons are discrete units. The neuron comprises various parts like dendrites (receiving signals), axons (transmitting signals), and myelin sheaths (accelerating transmission). Neural communication occurs via electrochemical processes, following the “all-or-none” principle. When a neuron reaches a specific threshold, it triggers an action potential, sending signals down the axon. The synapse bridges neurons, with neurotransmitters carrying signals across the synaptic cleft to receptor sites. Neurotransmitters regulate various functions, influencing mood, memory, and motor control.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Psychology as Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-1/itp-post-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 12:47:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-1/itp-post-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Psychology is the scientific study of mental processes and behavior. It systematically examines how the brain operates, its structure, and how it influences observable actions. To understand behavior, psychologists analyze three levels: the brain, the individual, and group dynamics. Psychological inquiry often contrasts scientific methods with intuition. Science relies on empirical data and systematic experimentation, while intuition involves more automatic and emotional thinking. Psychologists prefer empirical methods to ensure objectivity and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Introduction to Psychology&#39; Course Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 16:49:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course provides a broad overview of key concepts in psychology, exploring the scientific study of behavior and mental processes. Topics include brain function, sensation and perception, learning, memory, emotion, intelligence, personality, and social interactions. The course also examines psychological disorders, lifespan development, and the application of psychology in workplaces through industrial-organizational psychology. Students will gain a foundational understanding of psychological science and its practical applications in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
