<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Introduction to Psychology on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/introduction-to-psychology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Introduction to Psychology on Prof. Kirjakovski IBU Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 12:47:01 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/introduction-to-psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>LECTURE 1: Psychology as Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-1/itp-post-lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 12:47:01 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/lecture-1/itp-post-lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;lecture-summary&#34;&gt;Lecture summary:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Psychology is the scientific study of mental processes and behavior. It systematically examines how the brain operates, its structure, and how it influences observable actions. To understand behavior, psychologists analyze three levels: the brain, the individual, and group dynamics. Psychological inquiry often contrasts scientific methods with intuition. Science relies on empirical data and systematic experimentation, while intuition involves more automatic and emotional thinking. Psychologists prefer empirical methods to ensure objectivity and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#39;Introduction to Psychology&#39; Course Reading Materials</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/materials/materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 16:49:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/introduction-to-psychology/materials/materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;brief-course-description&#34;&gt;Brief course description:&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This course provides a broad overview of key concepts in psychology, exploring the scientific study of behavior and mental processes. Topics include brain function, sensation and perception, learning, memory, emotion, intelligence, personality, and social interactions. The course also examines psychological disorders, lifespan development, and the application of psychology in workplaces through industrial-organizational psychology. Students will gain a foundational understanding of psychological science and its practical applications in everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
